Register of the Ray Lyman Wilbur papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- SOCIAL PROBLEMS FILE, circa 1907-1958 (Boxes 109-141)
  - Education
    - Adult education
      - General
        - Group discussion. Organization and technique. Flyers, pamphlets, newsletters, letters, printed articles, clippings, reports, minutes, miscellany and books, 1935-1952 (Box-folder 132: 7)
        - Group discussion (Box-folder 133: 1-2)
      - California Association for Adult Education
        - General, 1939-1954 (Box-folder 133: 3)
        - Conference materials, 1937-1939 (Box-folder 133: 4-5)
        - Publications, 1937-1939 (Box-folder 133: 6)
        - Publications (Box-folder 134: 1)
      - California State Department of Education. Newsletters and reports, 1937-1942 (Box-folder 134: 2)
      - National Advisory Committee on Illiteracy. Bulletin, press releases, letters, notes, and form letters, 1929-1939
        - General
          - Non-printed material (Box-folder 134: 3)
          - Printed material (Box-folder 134: 4-5)
        - Correspondence (Box-folder 134: 6)
        - Correspondence (Box-folder 135: 1-5)
        - Minutes (Box-folder 135: 6-7)
        - Press releases (Box-folder 136: 1-2)
      - San Francisco Adult Educational Council. Letters, minutes and miscellany, 1939-1952 (Box-folder 136: 3)
    - Disabled. Letters and conference program, 1929-1932 (Box-folder 136: 4)
    - International
      - General. Pamphlets, memoranda and letters, 1919-1957 (Box-folder 136: 5-6)
      - Aid to Foreign Students. Primarily non-printed materials of various organizations, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 136: 7)
      - Committee on Friendly Relations Among Foreign Students. Letters, minutes, reports, pamphlets and newsletters, 1943-1946 (Box-folder 136: 8)
      - Conference of Allied Ministers of Education. Proposals, letters and constitution drafts (Box-folder 136: 9)
      - International Student Service. Letter and non-printed material, 1939-1941 (Box-folder 137: 1)
      - World Student Service Fund. Primarily newsletters, 1943-1948 (Box-folder 137: 2-3)
  - Labor and industrial relations. Primarily pamphlets, 1936-1948 (Box-folder 137: 4)
  - Labor and industrial relations (Box-folder 138: 1)
  - Public opinion. Bulletins, conference proceedings, printed articles, pamphlets, reports and a book, 1937-1946 (Box-folder 138: 2-8)
  - Race relations
    - General. Letters, pamphlets, clippings and miscellany, 1931-1948 (Box-folder 139: 1-2)
    - Blacks
      - General. Letters, pamphlets, reports, printed articles and miscellany, 1937-1951 (Box-folder 139: 3-5)
      - Education. Reports, 1935-1946 (Box-folder 139: 6)
      - Education (Box-folder 140: 1)
      - Health. Primarily typescript reports, 1928-1931 (Box-folder 140: 2-8)
    - Chinese. Report and printed article, 1934-1939 (Box-folder 141: 1)
    - Indians. Bulletins, letters, pamphlet, 1930-1945 (Box-folder 141: 2)
    - Jews. Pamphlet and printed article, 1944-1948 (Box-folder 141: 3)
    - Mexican-Americans. Report, 1947 (Box-folder 141: 4)
  - Social Security Act. Pamphlet, letters, newsletter, reprints and speeches primarily relating to geriatrics, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 141: 5)
  - Veterans. Letters, pamphlets, clippings and reports, 1929-1946 (Box-folder 141: 6-7)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1919-1956 (Boxes 141-142)
  Letters, clippings, conference materials, newsletters, notes, charts, speech transcripts, and miscellaneous printed material relating to the Mooney-Billings case, medicine and health insurance, radio and television broadcasting, and other topics, arranged by subject.
  - Aviation, 1942 (Box-folder 141: 8)
    Letter with attachments relating to air mail contracts.
  - Broadcasting, 1940-1956 (Box-folder 141: 9-10)
    Letters, plays, conference materials, and printed material relating to television and radio.
  - Conservation of fish, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 142: 1)
    Speech and printed material.
  - Medicine and health insurance, 1929-1949 (Box-folder 142: 2-4)
    Letters, clippings, printed material, conference material, and charts.
  - Mooney, Thomas, 1919-1939 (Box-folder 142: 5)
    Clippings, non-printed material, and correspondence with Thomas Mooney.
  - Movies, 1923-1953 (Box-folder 142: 6-7)
    Printed material relating to foreign movie industries, and newsletters relating to the Committee on Public Relations affiliated with the Motion Picture Producers and Distributors of America, Inc.
  - United States Naval Academy, 1930 (Box-folder 142: 8)
    Notes, letters, and printed material relating to football eligibility.
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL, 1924-1939 (Boxes 143-145)
  Serial issues, printed material, clippings, and a collection of wire reports relating to the Institute of Pacific Relations, international relations, the 1936 Olympics in Germany, and other topics, arranged by size.
  - Institute of Pacific Relations, clippings, 1924-1929 (Box 143)
  - A Tense World Speaks for Itself, 1938 (Box 144)
    Printed pamphlet with non-printed collection of wire reports (used as source material?) relating to events in Europe, primarily the Munich Conference and the partition of Czechoslovakia.
  - Primarily printed material relating to the 1936 Olympics in Germany (Box 145)
    Also includes a WPA progress report, a Boy Scouts booklet, and a book relating to the organization of the Interior Department.
- HERBERT HOOVER FILE II (Box 146)
  Access
  May not be used without permission of the Archivist.
  Materials previously separated from rest of collection.
  - Herbert Hoover pencil-drawn doodles (Box-folder 146: 1)
    General note
    Seven items, six of which are on White House stationery; small 16-mo and small 8-vo.
    - Shell-form doodle, 1931 January 9
    - Kite-form doodle, 1931 January 9
    - Elaborate triangle, 1931 April 3
    - Abstract doodle, 1930 February 7
    - Cone-form doodle, 1931 August 28
    - Oval doodle, 1930 November 14
    - Circular doodle, 1931 April 28
    - Mounted newspaper clipping from the San Francisco News showcasing Hoover's doodles, 1930
  - Hoover Library correspondence (Box-folder 146: 2)
    Relates to Herbert Hoover's interest in the Library of War and Peace at Stanford University. Most of the Herbert Hoover letters were written while he was Secretary of Commerce.
    - Typed Ls, 3 pp., Washington, from Herbert Hoover to R. L. Wilbur, 1923 September 1
      Letter shows Herbert Hoover's interest in scholarship, research, and administration.
    - Typed Ls, 1 p., 4-to, Stanford, Calif., from Lou Henry Hoover (Mrs. Hoover) to R. L. Wilbur, together with a typed copy of telegram from Herbert Hoover to Lou Henry Hoover, 1923 September 26
    - Typed Ls, 1 p., 4-to, from Edgar Rickard to R. L. Wilbur, 1924 January 2
    - Typed Ls, 2 pp., 4-to, Washington, from Herbert Hover to R. L. Wilbur, 1924 January 16
    - Typed Ls, 1 p., 4-to, Washington, from Herbert Hoover to R. L. Wilbur, 1923 September 14
    - Typed carbon L, 3 pp., 4-to, N.P., from R. L. Wilbur to Herbert Hoover, 1923 October 3
    - Typed carbon of an agreement, 4 pp., 4-to
    - Typed Ls, 1 p., 4-to, New York, from E. Rickard to R. L. Wilbur, together with two carbon copies of letters from Rickard to Herbert Hoover, 2 pp., 1923 December 4, 6, 8
    - Typed Ls, 2 pp., 4-to, Stanford, from librarian of Stanford University to R. L. Wilbur, 1923 October 8
    - Typed Ls, 1 p., 4-to. Washington, from Herbert Hoover to R. L. Wilbur, together with two typed carbon replies, 4 pp., 1923 December 20, 26 and 1924 January 3
    - Typed Ls, 1 p., 4-to, Washington, from Herbert Hoover to R. L. Wilbur, together with carbon reply, 1924 February 6, 12
    - Typed draft of organization of Hoover War Library, 2 pp., 4-to, N.P., pencil corrections, together with a typed plan of organization, 2 pp. 4-to, N.P., undated
    - Typed Ls, 1 p., 4-to, Stanford, from Herbert Hoover to R. L. Wilbur, together with typed draft, 5 pp., 4-to, N.P., by Herbert Hoover outlining the conditions of his gift to Stanford University, 1924 August 8, undated
    - Typed Ls, 1 p., 8-vo, Washington, from E. Rickard to R. L. Wilbur, together with two miscellaneous carbon and typed replies, 2 pp., 1932 November 28
    - Typed carbon L, 2 pp., 4-to, Washington, from Herbert Hoover to E. Rickard, 1932 November 30
    - Typed Ls, 2 pp., 4-to, New York, from E. Rickard to R. L. Wilbur, 1932 November 29
  - Correspondence between Wilbur and Hoover
    - General, 1933-1948 (Box-folder 146: 3)
      - Typed Ns, 1 p., 8-vo, N.P., from Herbert Hoover to R. L. Wilbur, 1933 October 21
      - Typed Ns, 1 p., 4-to, New York, from Herbert Hoover to R. L. Wilbur, 1937 September 17
      - Typed Ls, 1 p., 8-vo, New York, from Herbert Hoover to R. L. Wilbur, 1942 October 13
      - Typed Ls, 1 p., 8-vo, New York, from Herbert Hoover to R. L. Wilbur, together with a dictated letter, not sent nor signed from Herbert Hoover to Joseph Davies, 1943 August 13
      - Typed Ns, 1 p., 8-vo, New York, from Herbert Hoover to R. L. Wilbur, 1945 February 4
      - Typed Ns, 1 p., 8-vo, New York, from Herbert Hoover to R. L. Wilbur, 1945 February 10
      - Typed Ns, 1 p., 8-vo, New York, from Herbert Hoover to R. L. Wilbur, together with typed carbon reply and typed draft of letter to Herbert Hoover, 1948 February 7
    - Hoover Institution re: War Library Building, Dr. Karl Brandt, Stanford presidents (Box-folder 146: 4)
  - Handwritten manuscript plus typed carbon manuscript, "Herbert Hoover, A Personal Sketch," 29 pp., 4-to, N.P., undated (Box-folder 146: 5)
    With manuscript corrections by Herbert Hoover of article by R. L. Wilbur. See also Box 2, Folder 13.
  - Nominating speech for Herbert Hoover, 1928 June (Box-folder 146: 6)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1906-1941 (Photo file)
  38 prints / 6 envelopes; 3 framed photographs; 4 albums
  - Photo of International American Conference of Conciliation and Arbitration, Washington D.C.; photo of Marguerite Blake Wilbur, 1929 (Envelope mA)
  - Photo of Conference on Illiteracy members, 1929; photo of Ray Lyman Wilbur with unidentified group; photo of unidentified Allied officers and civilians, Berlin, 1919; 1 print of participants in the Yosemite Conference of the Institute of Pacific Relations, 1941 (Envelope m*B)
  - Framed portrait of Ray Lyman Wilbur, 1931; framed photo of Heidelberg Castle, Germany; framed photo of the Forum, Rome (Art rack)
  - 3 photo albums showing the construction of Hoover Dam, 1930-1932 (Album fC-E)
  - 1 print of Ray L. Wilbur, Stanford, 1906; 1 print of Ray L. Wilbur and others at the Pan-American Union, Washington D.C, 1929; 1 print of Ray L. Wilbur and others at the Pan-American Union, Washington D.C., 1930; 1 print of Ray L. Wilbur and others at the Pan-American Union, Washington D.C, 1932; 1 print of Gertrude Paist Naugler with children; 1 print of Teddy Naugler, 1940 (Envelope mF)
  - 6 prints taken at the Honolulu Conference of the Institute of Pacific Relations, 1925 (Envelope mG)
    Includes a photograph of Ray Lyman Wilbur, William Allen White, and other American participants.
  - Album of 51 prints of participants in the Honolulu Conference of the Institute of Pacific Relations, 1925 (Album fH)
  - 2 prints of President Herbert Hoover and his cabinet, 1929-1932; 5 prints of Ray Lyman Wilbur and others at Stanford University functions; 6 prints relating to an illiteracy clinic on the Blackfeet Indian Reservation, circa 1930; 3 prints and related material of organizers and exhibits at the Craterville Park State Indian Fair, Oklahoma, 1928; 1 print of Chao-Chu Wu (Chinese Ambassador to U.S.) and his wife, Pao-Fung, 1932; 1 print of an unidentified physician, 1 print of the inauguration of Laurence Judd as Governor of Hawaii, 1929 (Envelope mI)
- MEMORABILIA (Memorabilia cabinet)
  One model of Hoover Dam, one set of fossilized animal tracks, one Boy Scout statue, one blotter, one medicine ball, three medals, and one envelope of memorabilia.
- SOUND RECORDINGS, 1940 (Record cabinet)
  Four recordings of speeches by Dr. Wilbur.